<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE faq PUBLIC "+//IDN faq.org//DTD Frequently Asked Questions//EN//XML"
                     "http://xml.ascc.net/xml/resource/qaml-xml.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="qaml.css" ?>
<faq >
  <head>
     <title>
     The QAML FAQ
    </title>
    <maintain><name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
        <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </maintain>
    <hdr>
       <type>Programming</type>
       <content>FAQ, QAML, Frequently Asked Question,
      Question and Answer Markup Language,
       XML, SGML </content>
    </hdr>
    <archive href="http://www.ascc.net/xml/en/utf-8/camel-faq.xml"/>
  </head>
  <body  xml:lang="en">
  <section>
    <logo href="../../graphics/xml.gif" 
         alt="The XML Logo (from the XML FAQ)" />
    <title>
      The QAML F.A.Q.
    </title>
    <p>
      This FAQ is about QAML, a markup language for internet FAQs.
      </p>
      <p>QAML is the Question and Answer Markup Language.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
    <title>
      A. General
    </title>
  
<qna id='a1'><q class='h2' >
      A.1. What is a FAQ?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p> A FAQ is the nickname for a "Frequently Asked Questions"
    document. There are thousands of FAQs available on the World Wide Web
    on many different topics. The basic format of a FAQ is that someone
    asks a question, and someone else answers.
    </p>
    <p>FAQs were very popular on specialist bulletin boards, mailing lists
    and USENET newsgroups. On these discussion forums, the same questions
    appear repeatedly: newbies ask the same questions and new approaches to 
    solving problems get developed. These questions and answers are collected
    into FAQs; newbies can be directed to the FAQs for good answers, 
    and the FAQs can get updated. </p>
    <p>In several cases, FAQs are ultimately 
    revised into book form and published in paper: 
    <span class="i">The SGML FAQBook</span> by Steve DeRose and
    <span class="i">Chinese Japanese Korean Vietnamese Information Processing</span>
    by Ken Lunde are both examples of FAQs in book form.
    </p>
    <p>You can find a good collection of FAQs at the web site of 
    <span class="tt">faq.org</span>
    (<link href="http://www.faq.org">http://www.faq.org/</link>).
    </p>  
    </a>
</qna>    
<qna id='a2'><q class='h2' >
      A.2. What is a Markup Language?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>A markup language lets you name the various elements in your text:
    HTML is the most famous markup language. You just insert special
    codes called <span class="i">tags</span> into your text; these tags
    tell you where each interesting element starts or finishes.
    </p>
    <p>The term markup was coined by Dr Charles Goldfarb at IBM in the
    early 1970s. Goldfarb invented SGML, the Standard Generalized Markup
    Language (Internation Standard 8879:1986) which is now becoming 
    available over the WWW as XML, the Extensible Markup Language.
    </p>  
    </a>
</qna>
<qna id='a3'><q class='h2' >
      A.3. What is QAML?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>QAML is a markup language created specially to help write,
    use and maintain FAQs. It is smaller and simpler than HTML.
    </p>
    <p>A QAML document has a very simple structure: it has a
    <span class="tt">head</span> and a 
    <span class="tt">body</span>. The body is made up of
    <span class="tt">qna</span> elements, each of which has a
    <span class="tt">q</span> question and 
    <span class="tt">a</span> answer. 
    </p>
    <p>Because the questions and answers are clearly marked up
    by tags, it makes life a lot easier for people to write 
    programs to manipulate the FAQ: to automatically generate
    indexes of questions, to make global changes to stylesheets,
    or to split the questions and answers into different pages.
    </p>  
    </a>
</qna>
<qna id='a4'><q class='h2' >
      A.4. Who wrote QAML?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>QAML version 1.0 was written by Justin Higgens, of
    faq.org. Email <link href="mailto:jhiggins@dn.net">jhiggins@dn.net</link>.
    This version used SGML, and so is very lenient on tagging errors.
    </p>
    <p>QAML version 2.0 uses XML, and so you need to be more careful with
    providing all the tags needed for a well-formed XML document.                                                               
    It has very full support for the latest World Wide Web Consortium
    specifications (see <link href="http://www.w3.org">http://www.w3.org</link>).
    It was written by Rick Jelliffe, of the Academia Sinica Computing Center,
    Taipei, Taiwan.
    </p>  
    </a>
</qna>
                    
                    
<qna id='a5'><q class='h2' >
      A.5. Why not just use HTML?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>HTML is much more complicated and richer than QAML.
    However, HTML allows you to create documents which look
    pretty but which do not have the tagging needed to create
    indexes or to convert the data to different forms: it
    gives you too much!
    </p>
    <p>FAQ documents can be accessed from all sorts of systems,
    not only visual web browsers. So QAML does not provide
    the types of elements which cannot be seen on many different
    media: telnet terminals, Braille readers, speech synthesizers,
    mobile phones, etc.
    </p>
    <p>However, it is very easy to convert QAML to HTML. There
    are XSL stylesheets available to do this.  So you can write
    your FAQ in QAML, but deliver it in HTML.
    </p>  
    </a>
</qna>
                    


</section>
    <section>
    <title>
      B. About Writing QAML Documents
    </title>
  <qna id='b1'><q class='h2' >
      B.1. How can I write a QAML document?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>You can use any text editor, or SGML or HTML editor.
    The NotePad or WordPad applications allow it. You can
    use most word processors (but remember to save the 
    document as "Text".  You can even use a WYSIWYG HTML editor
    to create the FAQ, and then use a text editor to alter
    the element type names and attributes as appropriate.
    </p>
    <p>There is also an OmniMark script available which does
    automates much of the HTML-to-QAML conversion work.
    </p>
    <p>QAML Structure</p>
    <p>A QAML document has a very simple structure: it has a
    <span class="tt">head</span> and a 
    <span class="tt">body</span>. 
    </p>
    <p>The head has to have some 
    <span class="i">metadata</span>
    which gives the title, the maintainers name and email contact
    address, the official archive site for the FAQ, and 
    keywords which can be given to a search robot.
    </p>
    <p>The body is made up of
    <span class="tt">qna</span> elements, each of which has a
    <span class="tt">q</span> question and 
    <span class="tt">a</span> answer. 
    These qna elements can be collected into sections, and 
    given general section titles.
    </p>
    <p>Within each answer, you can have <span class="tt">p</span>
    paragraph elements. The only element types allowed inside
    a paragraph are <span class="tt">link</span> and
    <span class="tt">span</span>. 
    </p>
    <div class="ul">
    <p class="li">A link acts like a hypertext
    link in HTML: if you are using a hypertext browser, you
    should be able to click on it, and go to the location specified.
    If you are not using a hypertext browser, the link may only
    appear in a different color. (E.g., at the moment the CSS stylesheets
    for QAML do not support hypertext.)
    </p>
    <p class="li">The span element acts like its HTML inspiration.
    It lets you mark up a range of text inside a paragraph. You give
    it a class attribute to signify what its meaning is. Typically
    this will be used to select some font variation, such a bolding.
    However, please remember to write your FAQ so that it still makes
    sense to someone who is not using a big color screen and a fancy 
    web browser: use the formatting to 
    <span class="i">assist</span> the meaning of the text
    not to <span class="i">convey</span> it.
    </p>
    </div>
    </a>     
    
</qna>
<qna id='b2'><q class='h2' >
      B.2. What stylesheets are available for QAML?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>There is a default stylesheet available from
    Academia Sinica Computing Centre's Chinese XML Now!
    project, at 
    <link href="http://www.ascc.net/xml/en/utf-8/resource-index.html">
    http://www.ascc.net/xml/en/utf-8/resource-index.html</link>
    </p>
    </a>
</qna>
<qna id='b3'><q class='h2' >
      B.3. How can I make a hypertext link?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>The link element has an attribute called href. 
    Just put in the URL of the resource that is the
    link's target.
    </p>
    <p>Remember that the data inside the link should also
    contain the URL. This is because some people may
    read the FAQ from a paper printout. Don't forget them!
    </p>
    <p>An example follows.</p>
    <p class="pre">
    &lt;p&gt;This is &lt;link href="qaml-faq.xml"&gt;qaml-faq.xml&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    </p>
    <p>(Some WWW browsers may display that example wrong, so another
    version of the same thing follows: the one with the angle brackets is
    the correct one.)</p>
    <p class="pre">
    <![CDATA[<p>This is <link href="qaml-faq.xml">qaml-faq.xml</link></p>]]>
    </p>
    </a>
</qna>
</section>
    <section>
    <title>
      C. Processing QAML documents
    </title>
  
<qna id='c1'><q class='h2' >
      C.1. What can I use QAML documents for?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>
    </p>
    
    </a>
</qna>
<qna id='c2'><q class='h2' >
      C.2. What are text processing languages?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>
    </p>
    
    </a>
</qna>
    
    
</section>
    <section>
    <title>
      D. QAML and Standards
    </title>
    
    
<qna id='d1'><q class='h2' >
      D.1. Are Standards Useful?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>Standards are very useful, because they allow
    us to build amazing things co-operatively.
    </p>
    <p>But a standard is usually general purpose,
    and a general-purpose tool is usually sub-optimal
    than a custom-made, specific-purpose tool.
    So  QAML is better for representing FAQs than
    HTML, but your own markup language will be even
    better for marking up <span class="b">your</span>
    own FAQ.</p>
    <p>But if you make your own markup language,
    you have to also then write all your own computer
    tools to use it. However, QAML is very simple, so
    even if you do have your own markup language for
    FAQs, you may find it is not difficult to export
    your information into QAML format, so that you can
    use any QAML tools. Or you may find you can convert
    QAML tools for your requirements too!
    </p>                 
    </a>
</qna>

    
<qna id='d2'><q class='h2' >
      D.2. What is XML??
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>XML is the Extensible Markup Language. It is a
    simple syntax for constructing markup languages to
    exchange data over the WWW. QAML 2.0 documents are
    XML documents. (And XML documents are SGML documents.)
    </p>
    <p>See <link href="http://www.w3.org/">http://www.w3.org/</link>
    for more details.</p>
    </a>
</qna>

    
<qna id='d2a'><q class='h2' >
      D.2a. What is I18n??
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>I18n is the contraction used to mean "internationalization",
    because there are 18 letters missing.</p>
    <p>I18n means the features available to allow documents
    in different languages, perhaps even within the same document.
    </p>
    <p>QAML 2.0 is highly internationalized, following WWW best practise. 
    (One of QAML 2.0's authors is a member of the World Wide Web Consortium's
    I18n Interest Group, and proposed most of the i18n features of XML.)
    It currently does not have support for bi-directional text; this
    can be added on request. 
    </p>
    <p>QAML 2.0 documents can use any standard character encoding, and all
    elements can have an attribute <span class="tt">xml:lang</span>
    to give the language being used.
    </p>
    </a>
</qna>

<qna id='d3'><q class='h2' >
      D.3. What is Accessability??
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>Accessability means that the document can be read by people
    on unusual mediums or formats: large magnifaction screens,
    speech synthesizers, Braille readers and so on.
    </p>
    <p>QAML has been written following the World Wide Web Consortium
    guidelines in this area: elements with vision-dependencies have
    kept out, and logo images must have alternative forms.
    </p>
    </a>
</qna>

<qna id='d4'><q class='h2' >
      D.4. What is Dublin Core?
    </q><author>
                <name>Rick Jelliffe</name>
                <email>ricko@gate.sinica.edu.tw</email>
        </author> <a>
    <p>The Dublin Core is a basic set of 13 elements which 
    various experts have decided are a minimum useful list
    for capturing basic metadata about small documents on
    the Web. This metadata allows searching by users and
    rudamentary classification by librarians. 
    </p>
    <p>The QAML DTD (Document Type Definition) shows the
    mappings to the various Dublin Core elements. Also, we
    encourage the use of a final section, with class <span
    class="tt">dc</span>, with explicit markup of the 
    Dublin Core elements. This assists users of printed
    versions of your FAQ.
    </p>
    <p>For more information on Dublin Core, there is a
    small QAML FAQ on Metadata at
    <link href="http://www.ascc.net/xml/en/utf-8/dc-fq.xml">
    http://www.ascc.net/xml/en/utf-8/dc-fq.xml</link>.
    </p>
    </a>
</qna>
</section>
    <section class="dc">
    <title>
      Cataloging Information (Dublin Core)
    </title>
<p class='pre'  xml:space='preserve' >
&lt;DC:TITLE       xml:lang="en"&gt;The QAML FAQ &lt;/DC:TITLE&gt;
&lt;DC:CREATOR                  &gt;Rick Jelliffe &lt;/DC:CREATOR&gt;
&lt;DC:SUBJECT     xml:lang="en"&gt;FAQ, QAML, Frequently Asked Question,
      Question and Answer Markup Language, XML, SGML 
                              &lt;/DC:SUBJECT&gt;
&lt;DC:DESCRIPTION xml:lang="en"&gt;Frequently Asked Questions about using QAML, 
                              the Question and Answer Markup Language &lt;/DC:DESCRIPTION&gt;
&lt;DC:PUBLISHER   xml:lang="en"&gt;Computing Centre, Academia Sinica, Taiwan &lt;/DC:PUBLISHER&gt;
&lt;DC:TYPE        xml:lang="en"&gt;Text.Article &lt;/DC:TYPE&gt;
&lt;DC:DATE                     &gt;1999-04-06 &lt;/DC:DATE&gt;
&lt;DC:RIGHTS                   &gt;<link href= 
"http://www.ascc.net/xml/en/utf-8/legal.html">
http://www.ascc.net/xml/en/utf-8/legal.html</link >
&lt;/DC:RIGHTS&gt;
</p>
</section>
  </body>
</faq>

